there's a lot of money on the line here
winning first place gets you 25,000 lb
it's almost $32,000 but there are also
bonuses for breaking the ipf world
record it's like yeah Quant can hold his
own with any of these guys and it's
really good to see him in contention and
I'm I'm excited to see the semi-finals
and the games in 20124 the guy still has
an impact and his career is still one
that we talk about and are working to
contextualize hey folks welcome to
strength weekly the show that brings you
all the news that you need from around
the barbell game and and honestly some
news you didn't know you need but you
definitely want I'm one of your hosts
David Thomas to joined by the Intrepid
the incomparable the very smart and also
incredibly kind Phil Blackman Phil how
are we feeling this week about these hot
hot hot stories and hotter takes we have
on strength week uh it was a lot of
massive downpour in Miami for the first
CrossFit competition of the year and uh
it was it was hot it was hot so we're
going to get into it let's get into it
your strength weekly run of show our top
story today is actually from 2015 before
he served a lengthy doping suspension
weightlifter Ilia ilen almost clean and
jerk 247 kg we also have results from W
paloa Miami the first major competition
in not only the CrossFit calendar this
year but the strength sports calendar
and then do you think you're really
strong well Larry Wheels is one of the
strongest people in the world and might
not have been strong enough for Pilates
finally Jesus olivz squats a ridiculous
amount of weight for five it might be
the heaviest set of five in the rawb
squat we've ever seen at least that I've
ever seen bill which of these stories
are you most excited about 2024 water
paloa Miami for a bunch of different
reasons not only is it the first of two
water palas this year which we'll get
into but like some of the performances
were really impressive and are
indicative of what's to come for the
rest of the CrossFit season all right
well let's get into our first story
which is all about the clicks what you
really want to see it's a clip that's
only a few seconds long but but it took
the Internet by storm it is Ilia Ilan of
Kazakhstan in 2015 preparing for the
President's Cup in grne Russia clean and
jerked in training or attempted to clean
and jerk
247 kilograms now he weighed 105
kilograms or around that at the time
this was not like an official
competition this was in training at that
competition he set a new massive world
record in that weight category with a
246 kgam cleaning Jerk It is a legendary
lift it was the top weight lifted in his
storyed weightlifting career now I want
to point out Ilia Ilan did serve a
lengthy doping suspension sometime after
this did not compete at the 2016 Rio
Olympics because retests of his samples
from the 2008 2012 Olympics came back
positive and he was stripped of his gold
medals let's contextualize this so for a
period of nearly a decade starting when
he was 17 years old Ilan was undefeated
in international competition at the
senior level he won his first senior
World Championship when he was just 17
won the Olympics in 2008 and 2012 as a
94 kilo lifter had that on lock after
the 2012 Olympics in London actually
moved up a weight class to the 105
kilogram division this was before weight
class restructuring and dominated that
at the international level was
undefeated and then at the President's
Cup in gry in 2015 pulled out this 246
kilogram clean iner to really redefine
what folks thought was possible in that
weight category and then the comes off
the tracks after that after doping
retests and he was present at the Rio
Olympics as a spectator but did not
compete because he was serving a doping
suspension this makes ilan's career one
of the most complex in weightlifting
history because for a time he was
considered like the ultimate
weightlifting Prodigy he was someone who
many folks had in the conversation while
he was still active while he was still
in his mid 20s as potentially the
greatest weightlifter of all time and
after he served his doping suspension he
did get back into weightlifting was not
able to achieve nearly the success and
really wasn't even competing for medals
at the international level and then
retired after the Tokyo Olympics were
postponed due to covid Phil curious is
someone who kind of came to string
Sports coverage after the peak of ilan's
career what is your impression of this
lifter and what do you remember first
learning about him you know in 2018 2019
yeah when I first got uh came on board
at barbend covering those doping
scandals that came out from those
retests were really one of the first
like extensive beats that I covered and
it felt like I was writing a doping
story six times a week with how much
coverage there was of each doping
Scandal what I found was that even
though he was serving his doping
suspension he was still very much active
on his YouTube on his training platforms
to like display how to properly lift and
all this stuff and like you can tell how
like quality form that he had and that
only exacerbated how complex the issue
became because you're like man not only
does this guy get it and not only does
his you know joints have more
flexibility than any other person I've
ever seen in the entire European region
but like okay he's the top in the world
but he also now is forever going to be
tainted by the fact that he had these
doping retests that claimed his Golds so
he becomes in my mind one of those
figures of we'll never actually know
because you can't rewrite history but
yeah is he the goat would you place him
as the goat I I I love that
discussion he was exciting he was
exciting he would get pumped up you know
he was this young Lifter on the scene um
who really played to the crowd he was
dancing on stage in training you'd see
him dancing to techno between you know
attempts at world record weights it was
really something and this was before
social media was as prevalent so we
weren't seeing training videos every
week from these athletes now you know
the top lifters they're posting training
videos they want to up their social
followings they have sponsors who want
to leverage that reach Ilan you know he
was a celebrity still is a celebrity in
his native Kazakhstan but it wasn't like
he was dropping training videos every
day like we see with a lot of
international Elite lifters today the
training footage would come out in bits
and spurts but it it wasn't you weren't
really seeing his training updates in
real time you never knew exactly what
kind of strength he was bringing to the
stage until you saw him in competition
no one at around 105 kilos kilos body
weight in competition is attempting
anywhere near 246 247 kilos today I just
want to point out this is significantly
above the weights we're seeing thrown
around in competition today doping
controls gotten more stringent
anti-doping technology has gotten more
advanced so take that as you will just
worth noting this video took the
Internet by storm over eight years after
it was recorded yeah I mean this came
out early 2024 so the guy still has an
impact and his career is still one that
we talk about and our working to
contextual I in weightlifting history
today let's move on water paloa an event
that recently happened not something
that happened over eight years ago
waterl Miami there are now two water
ples in in the calendar which is going
to take me a while to get into my thick
skull water PLO Miami 20124 Phil tail of
the tape who won so at Bayfront Park in
Miami uh on the elite side we have Emma
Carey for the women coming up with a
huge win with 458 points second was
Gabriel Malla with 452 points and Daniel
Brandon getting on the Podium at 435 a
half points she came up big in the
handstand walk in all the gymnastic
events like she normally does and that
helped her push her over the top with a
big 100 Point uh event to get onto the
podium on the men's side Ricky Gard
man's back in it bronze at the games
wins here at w paloa he beat Brent
fikowski who got in the silver medal
spot and Sam Quan back on the podium
with 43 points welcome back Sam is this
his biggest Podium finish since his
second place finish at the 2020 games
the pandemic games this is his Podium
finish since then yes like this this
this is this is the sign that Quant a
player this season oh yeah qu's back he
is back baby oh yeah he's back oh my God
this is gard's second victory in a row
correct this is gard's second Victory he
has been consistently performing well he
did get injured recently and so he was
coming back off of that injury so this
was really the test to see how well he
had recovered from that and clearly he
recovered well and he's performing to
literally the top end W paloa is known
for its team events which are uh Team
trios events it's three members per team
and that is really the headliner of
water paloa it's really what sets it
apart from something like the games or
any of the rest of the CrossFit season
so a lot of The Prestige is looked at
over on the team side and because of
that a lot of the big individual
athletes will also compete on teams
rather than an individual competition
technically they're still in their
offseason the CrossFit open doesn't
start until late February so as athletes
are building their engines and getting
back up to that they won't necessarily
compete in individual water Pala they'll
compete on a team because the workload
is a little bit more spread and it's a
bit easier of a lift so to speak than
competing on the individual side however
Gard was like you know what I'm gonna do
you know what I'm gonna do David I'm I'm
Ricky Gard I'm one of the best in the
world he's like I'm gonna win on the
individual side and then I'm also gonna
compete on the team side wait okay so
how how did the scheduling work for
those who for those who weren't watching
the entire thing how did that how did
that work out scheduling wise did he
have to bounce back in fourth between
events no so the schedule from the 11th
through the 14th the first two days of
competition it was individuals and then
the second two days of competition it
was teams now there were some
adjustments made to the competition due
to rain uh it was raining all weekend in
Miami up and down the Eastern Seaboard
was bad weather in my remote area of New
York a lot of snow down in Miami a lot
of rain so uh they had to adjust a bunch
of the workouts for that so the
individuals did five workouts which is
not a lot in terms of being able to move
up and down the leaderboard like every
event really really really really really
counts and then on the team side they
did six events so first two days
individuals second two days teams
well what's the tail of the tape on the
team side the tail of the tape on the
team side so we'll get Ricky Gard out of
the way here he competed on team tier
and they got fourth place so just off
the podium on the men's side so Ricky
Gard had a pretty impressive weekend on
the women's side it was stronger than
the 90s Trend Captain by Kelsey Keel
they got 540 points to win for the
women's teams friend of the Pod uh over
on barbend and then on the team on the
men's side it was team goad which is
pretty significant because guess who was
the captain of that team who was the
captain of that team Phil two time Fest
man on Earth Justin mados is coming back
in he leads team goad to the victory
over Roman kov who was the silver
medalist at the games for the LA last
couple of years on team pixel and then
om ombre ombres which we'll get into I
think is the most indicative for what we
can expect for team competition at the
games because two of their athletes are
already slated to compete together for
that time and this was really their uh
first showing together to see how well
they can perform and they performed
really well I want to dig on a few
things here and I love that you
contextualize this Phil because it's the
teams are have become the focus at w PL
Miami it hasn't always been the case but
they are really the focus now so it is
indicative of some how some individuals
are doing on the individual side
although with five events you know it
was a very short competition truncated
this year the team side you know it's
tough to tell like how fit is Justin
mados right now competing on a team
tough to like pull out or isolate those
individual performances but I do want to
dig into a few names here uh Daniel
Brandon making the podium as an
individual Daniel Brandon is someone
we've seen sniff the podium in top
competition before and she is always in
the running and always in the
conversation as one of the best cross
hitters on the planet but to see her
actually make the podium there have been
a few games where she's kind of gotten
tripped up right she's fallen out of
Podium contention in the final days of
competition to see your Secura bronze
medal here really leaning into her
strengths on the gymnastics elements
really impressive stuff how did she look
for you on the weekend Dan brenon was
very impressive for me all weekend I
think it's she's one of those athletes
where I I look at her in a similar vein
that I look at some like strongman
athletes with their Signature Events so
like anytime you know that Tom stman is
going to step onto the uh onto the field
to play with the atlas Stones you know
he's winning that event and it's very
similar with Daniel brandan with
anything that involves gymnastics if
there's a handstand walk you know Daniel
Brandon's doing it four times faster
than anybody else and it's not going to
be close and all of the other athletes
need to calibrate that they aren't going
to be able to get top points in one of
those events unless Daniel Brandon has
some kind of huge mistake uh that like
botches that event so there isn't really
anybody else with any other kind of
event that jumps out to me as like
clearly the favorite every time it
happens and there's always gymnastic
events there's always the a handstand
walk featured at these major events in
some capacity so the fact that Daniel
Brandon going into any big CrossFit
event in my mind already has a 100 Point
event secured is a is is a Telltale sign
that it's like okay all she has to do is
fix some of those weaknesses because
she's already so far ahead in the other
aspects of of the game okay and Samuel
Quant dial in on Samuel qu because we
have not seen seen him on the podium in
almost four years good to see him back
it's great to see Sam back I I'm the
2020 CrossFit games were uh unique ones
in that there was a cut to the top five
so they could compete on the ranch
because we were amidst lockdowns due to
covid-19 and so he gets he makes the cut
into the top five and then he gets
second place but then he doesn't have
any big finishes immediately thereafter
the story really became Justin mados who
then went from third place at that in
the 2020 games wins back-to-back games
the following two years it's not like he
was you know totally out of contention
he had top 15 finishes at the games like
you know I mean he's still an elite
Athlete on the on the planet but it
didn't have the same resonance because
he was right next to Justin mados on
that Podium who then had back-to-back
wins so you know was that just a random
one-off year that he made the top five
cut and then that you know sort of
pushed him up the the rankings that he
otherwise wouldn't have gotten and I
love that he podiumed here because he
sort of put that kind of uh speculation
to rest it's like yeah Quant can hold
his own with any of these guys and it's
really good to see him in contention and
I'm I'm excited to see him be the big
man again on the floor come the
semi-finals and the games in
2024 Samu Samuel Quant definitely
someone a friend of the friend of the
brand as well been on the barbin podcast
someone I love watching Let's uh move on
because talking about the big man Larry
Wheels who has competed in about
everything except for CrossFit he's and
weightlifting he's competed in
powerlifting strong man arm wrestling I
think he got a little humbled recently
and I bring this up and we added this to
the roster today for the top story not
necessarily because it's breaking news
but because it's something that we have
been talking about for weeks on strength
weekly
Phil if people think they're strong what
is a one-way
ticket to Humble toown oh you want to go
to Humble toown you think you're strong
yeah go take a Pilates CL go step on a
revolver and then step off of it unable
to walk and tell me you're strong you
ain't strong a reformer reformer I think
you mean a revolver would be
pilates pilates revolver you can tell
how no it's a reformer you're right you
can tell how I feel about when I take a
pilates class buddy dude like the the
the last time I took a pilates class I
couldn't move I couldn't move I squat
heavy David I
squat you ain't strong if you ain't take
Pilates you ain't strong you ain't
strong I'm gonna be rude and read off
the script cuz there were some great
quotes look we'll have some clips from
the video you should definitely read
more about it on barbend you can find
the embedded video there like you know
Larry will link to the video you know
Larry did a great job being vulnerable
one thing I like about Larry Wheels one
of the strongest people on the planet
alltime world record holder in
powerlifting he's not afraid to be
vulnerable he's not afraid to go outside
his comfort zone and say hey there are
disciplines where I don't Excel and
there are ways that I am challenged as
an athlete and I love the vulnerability
there and I love that he's willing to
say like cool I'm gonna go outside of my
domain of expertise and experience and
I'm going to push myself and I'm going
to bring that to you I love some of
these quotes this feels like a hospital
bed in reference to being on the
reformer I expected Pilates to be
challenging but I didn't know how much
this is very eye opening again showing
that vulnerability that openness to
trying new things and exploring new
domains they were doing the short box ab
exercise everything is the opposite of
what I've been told to do as a
powerlifter the thing that jumped out to
me about this is that since Larry his
his Target for 2024 is to get his ifbb
Pro card what I like about him trying
Pilates strong man and powerlifting
you're training the movement you're not
training the muscles and in bodybuilding
you have to train the muscles not
necessarily the movement so a lot of the
time when you're training for
hypertrophy and training for
bodybuilding you're not going to be
training for efficiency of movement
because you want to work the muscles
through their lengthened and shortened
positions to really maximize the
stimulus so that they can grow and what
Pilates will do to people who are not
fully accustomed to it is they will
train your muscles in positions you
didn't know they could go in and that's
how you know you ain't strong that's how
you know you Ain you you Ain pilat you
ain't pilat strong you ain't a rounded
athlete you got weaknesses you got
weaknesses buddy you you know what's
harder than getting your ifbb pro card
Pilates
David I'm not I'm not touching that one
we we're moving we're moving we're
moving on we're gonna get off of our
we're gonna get off of our reinforced
Soap Box because we are both thick boys
and we're gonna talk about Jesus Olivera
preparing for the Sheffield the 2024
Sheffield Phil just quick context what
is the Sheffield so the Sheffield event
is arguably one of the biggest
powerlifting events of the year now in
my mind given the quality of athlete
that it invites an Invitational
Tournament that invites some of the top
athletes from uh major competitions over
the course of the previous year so uh
olis won this last year and it's not a
full-on powerlifting competition where
you compete against others in your
division what you do is you're competing
to try and put on the closest total to
the world record in your weight class
and then you are scored based on that
across the table so it does allow the
competition to compare people across
weight classes because they're competing
against their own weight classes world
record and you know who has the world
record in the super heavyweight category
who who would that be Phil I believe
it's olaris in pretty much
everything well he is certainly showing
that his squat is in form heading into
the Sheffield because he hit 400
kilograms at 882 pounds not for a single
not for a double but for five five five
882 pounds for five and it looked good
and it was it was raw right this is raw
with sleeves not wraps this is raw ipf
this is classic ipf right like you gotta
walk the weight out you can't wear WPS
no monoliths right no wraps you just get
sleeves a belt and he also wore wrist
wraps because why wouldn't you because
you have to hold nearly 900 pounds on
your back for a set of five he made it
look good he made it look good this is a
man who does not get called on depth a
lot at Powerlifting Meets cuz he's he's
sinking these I love that the Sheffield
is kind of a Level Playing Field right
you get to see super Heavies compete
against the lighter weight classes Etc
because they're competing against the
world record marks there's a lot of
money on the line here winning first
place gets you 25,000 pounds that's
almost $32,000 but there are also
bonuses for breaking the ipf world
record at the Sheffield if Oliver's were
to win and set World Records he could
make almost almost
$60,000 for like one meat it is also not
out of the r of possibility that
oliveres could actually do what you just
said and break in that kind of coin for
one event his training over the last uh
several weeks leading up to the
Sheffield on February 10th has been
spectacular he will go for World Records
he owns two of them he's going to go he
might call for a world record squat on
the bar which is the one that he doesn't
have the way that that tournament is set
up you are incentivized any athlete at
the Sheffield is incentivized to always
be going for as much as they possibly
can because all of the incentives in are
just for the biggest possible lifts that
you can make across each of the three
big lifts and then also for the total so
there isn't like oh this person hit this
I'm just G to go like one kilo over even
though I maybe could go heavier because
I just want to try and secure the win no
even if you have the win you're still
incentivized to go for a world record
because there's more money on the line
it is very well set up for us Spectators
to see the biggest possible list from
the best athletes in the game and I
think so far look I don't know all the
economics behind it I'm not the event
organizer and I don't want to speculate
too much but from a spectator standpoint
as someone who follows this stuff
closely and is passionate about this I
think this format has been a resounding
success thus far yeah 100% agree I I
only expect the Sheffield to get more
and more popular over the next handful
of years gets the best athletes and has
the biggest prize purse like what more
can you expect or would want from that
kind of meat I don't want anything more
and I'm not asking for anything more so
the Sheffield will be tuning in on us
time but it happens in the Jolly Old UK
Phil that has been strength weekly for
this blustery cold well not cold Miami
but cold for a lot of the country cold
week in January we are off to the races
as a string sports calendar heats up to
keep us warm heading further into 2024
until next week I'm David Thomas tow I'm
Phil Blackman thank you everybody for
joining we're going to get a lot more uh
exciting strength weeklys coming up as
the seasons for all of the big strength
Sports really heat up in February so
stick around you're not going to want to
miss anything that's happening in 2024
more of this I got to do some more curls
I got to get a pum before these you
should do
[Music]
Pilates